(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone, welcome back
to English Pod, my name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna be bringing
you another great sports lesson.
- Yes, this one is for all our hockey fans.
- I know we have a lot
of listeners from Russia,
so this is a very popular
sport in Russia, Czech Republic.
- Yes.
- So Canada.
- And Canada, right?
Very, very popular in Canada.
- It's our national game.
(laughing)
- Well, I guess 'cause
you guys have so much ice.
- I know, there's nothing else to do.
- It's skiing and hockey.
- All right, so it's gonna
be a really fun lesson.
We're gonna have a
lot of great vocabularies.
So before we start in the dialogue,
let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
- Very cablery preview.
- Well, we have three words for you now.
The first one, really
simple, puck, puck, puck.
P-U-C-K.
- So it's almost like duck, but not the P.
- Yes.
- And this is actually kind of like
the ball that you use in hockey.
- But it's not a ball.
- It's flats.
- It's flat and round.
- And round.
- So it looks like a disc,
kind of like a mini frisbee.
- Yes.
- And this is what the players do.
This is what they chase this around.
- They chase it, yeah.
- So in basketball, you have a ball.
In soccer, you have a ball.
In hockey, you have a puck.
- Yep.
- Okay, our next word.
- Key game.
- A key game.
- So this word key.
- Important.
- It means important.
- Really important.
- Yeah.
- So I can say a key game
is a really important game.
- Exactly.
You could also maybe say a key player.
- Key player is a really important player.
- Or even a key goal.
- Key goal, okay.
So let's take a look at our last word now.
Finals.
- Finals.
- So the finals are the last games.
- That's right.
And the winner of the
finals wins the championship.
- Okay.
For example, in the World Cup in soccer,
there's only one game played in the finals.
So after everyone gets eliminated, there's
one game where the winner is the champion.
- Yes.
- Okay.
So now we're ready
to listen to our dialogue
and it's gonna be a
little bit faster than
usual, because it's a
sports commentator, right?
- And it's exciting.
And there's a lot of action.
So don't worry about it.
Listen to it, and then we'll come back
and talk about some of the vocabulary.
(upbeat music)
- Oh, everyone, I'm Rick Fields,
and here with me is Bob Copeland.
- Howdy folks, and welcome to today's game.
You know, Rick, today's a key
game between Russia and Canada.
As you know, the winner
will move on to the finals.
- That's right.
And it looks like we're just
about ready to start the match.
The ref is calling the
players for the face off.
And here we go.
The Russians win position and
immediately start up their attack.
Federal gets checked hard into the boards.
But he's gonna shout has the puck now,
and he passes at the center, he shoots!
- Wow, what a save by the goalie!
- All right, the puck is back in play now.
- Have a glorious on a brick with.
- He is flying down the ice.
- The defenders can't keep up.
- Slap shot, he scores.
- What an amazing goal!
(crowd cheering)
(upbeat music)
- All right, so the Canadians
versus the Russians, huh?
- It reminds me of a classic, classic game.
- Exactly, the classic match.
- Yep.
- So let's take a look at
some of the vocabulary
that we heard in the
dialogue in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- We have five phrases in
language takeaway today.
And the first one is face off.
- Face off.
So Marco, a face off here is a noun, right?
- It's a noun.
- Exactly, and it's, so in
the beginning of a match,
the two players will
stand face to face, right?
That's why it's called kind of a face off.
And the referee will drop the puck.
- Yes.
- And they'll try to get it.
- Exactly, so that's the face off.
- The face off.
- Yep.
- Okay, let's take a look at our next word.
- Check, check, to check, to check.
So an interesting verb here, hey?
- Yeah, it's really interesting
because it's different from the way
that you would say check or revise, right?
- Yes, yeah.
- This is actually kind of a violent move.
- Yeah.
- So what do you do?
- It's basically in hockey, you take your
body and you hit another person with it.
- Okay, so to check someone
is to hit them with your body.
- With your body, right?
- You can't use your arms
or your legs or your hands.
You can only hit them like with your
shoulder or your hip, or the hip check.
- Okay.
- So yeah, it's very cool.
- All right.
- Our next word, goalie, goalie, goalie.
- Goalie is a person.
- Right, and probably the
bravest of the hockey match.
- No kidding.
- So why don't you tell
us what the goalie does?
- The goalie prevents the
puck from coming in the net.
- From going into the goal, right?
- So the goalie stops the
other team from getting a goal.
- A goal.
- Okay, so the goalie prevents the goals.
All right, very interesting.
Now our fourth word is related to goalie.
- Yes.
- Save. - Save.
- A-save, yeah.
- It's a noun here. - It's a noun here.
- So the goalie makes saves.
- That's right.
When he stops a goal, he makes a save.
- Makes a save, right?
- Yeah.
- Okay, we have some examples, so we
can understand this form of using save.
- Yes.
- Example one.
- That was an unbelievable save.
- Example two.
- The goalie didn't make the save.
- Example three.
- What a save.
The Russians win.
- Yeah, a little bit unusual here
that save is a noun instead of a verb,
but I think those examples were helpful.
- Mm-hmm.
Now let's take a look at
our last word, breakaway.
- Breakaway. - Breakaway.
- A breakaway.
- Okay, so you have two words
there that we know already, break.
- Yes.
- Right, and away.
- Yeah.
- So what are these two
words together actually mean?
- Well, imagine a group of hockey players
all fighting to get the puck, right?
And then one player breaks
off, breaks out of the group.
Yeah, yeah, and he skates down the ice
and he has the puck, and he's
far away from the other players.
- Right, right.
- He's going away from
the other players by himself.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so breakaway, all right.
So we've looked at a lot
of hockey language here,
and I think it's time now to
listen to our dialogue again.
This time we're gonna
slow it down a little bit.
- Yeah, I think this will help you to
understand these words a little bit better.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone.
I'm Rick Fields, and here
with me is Bob Copeland.
Howdy folks, and welcome to today's game.
You know, Rick, today is a key
game between Russia and Canada.
As you know, the winner
will move on to the finals.
- That's right, and it looks like we're
just about ready to start the match.
The ref is calling the players
for the face-off, and here we go.
The Russians win possession
and immediately set up their attack.
Federal have gets checked
hard into the boards.
- Well, he's the shot has the puck
now, and passes it to the center.
He shoots, "Wow, what
a save by the goalie!"
- All right, the puck is back in play now.
Pavel Bure is on a breakaway.
He is flying down the ice.
The defenders can't keep up.
Slap shot, he scores.
- What an amazing goal.
- Okay, this dialogue is interesting
because we have commentators narrating
or describing what's
happening in that moment, right?
- Yeah, and they're using some
interesting grammar, aren't they?
- Exactly, they are, because some
actions are happening in that moment,
but we notice something
a little bit strange.
- All right, well, let's look at
it and grammar breakdown.
- Grammar breakdown.
- Okay, let's listen to this sentence
that we previously heard in the dialogue.
- Moheesry shot has the puck
now, and passes it to the center.
He shoots.
Moheesry shot has the puck
now, and passes it to the center.
He shoots.
- I noticed that he's using
the present simple, right?
- Yeah.
- Even though the action
is now, it's in present simple.
- Yes, even though the action
is happening in that moment,
he's not using the present
progressive, because it continues.
- Yeah, this is because if you
notice, the actions are very, very brief.
- And fast.
- And exciting.
- Exactly, so you don't really have enough
time to say, for example, he is shooting.
- Yes.
- Because it's only one quick action.
He shoots the puck very fast, right?
Or for example, you wouldn't
really say he is passing.
- Yeah, he is passing the puck, right?
It's just one quick action.
He takes it and passes it,
and the action is finished.
- Yes, I think we can see a
few more examples of this.
Let's listen again.
- The Russians win possession
and immediately set up their attack.
The Russians win possession
Here, we can hear that
he is using the present
simple again, because
these are very short actions
that finish quickly, right?
- Exactly.
- And it's actually very, very common
when you're describing something you see,
that's happening now,
that's really exciting.
It's common to use present simple.
- Exactly, if you pay attention, most
sporting events are in the same way, right?
They would describe the
actions that are happening
in the present simple,
not present progressive.
- Yeah, but Marco, you have an example
of some present progressive here, right?
- Yes, let's listen to this sentence.
- He is flying down the ice.
He is flying down the ice.
- Now, we heard the sentence,
he is flying down the ice, right?
Now, this one is in progressive.
- Yeah, why is that?
- Well, first of all,
when we say he's flying
down the ice, it's not
that he's literally flying.
- No, he's not an airplane.
- He's just skating really fast, right?
So we kind of exaggerating and
we say, "Oh, he's flying down the ice.
" But he's actually skating.
So this is a progressive
action, so he is doing it.
- It's happening for more than one second.
- Yeah, exactly.
So that's why we would
say he is flying down the ice.
Instead of, he flies down the ice.
- Yes, yep.
- Unless it was like
really, really, really fast.
- Okay.
Okay, so here we see
that sometimes in English,
we do use present simple to talk
about what's happening now, right?
When it's happens really, really quickly
or when we want to show
that it's really exciting.
- Exactly.
Yeah, makes it much more exciting
if we just use the present simple.
- Yeah.
- Okay, let's listen to this
exciting dialogue one more time
and we'll come back
and talk a little bit more.
(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone, I'm Rick Fields
and here with me is Bob Copeland.
- Howdy folks and welcome to today's game.
You know, Rick, today's a key
game between Russia and Canada.
As you know, the winner
will move on to the finals.
- That's right, and it looks like we're
just about ready to start the match.
The ref is calling the
players for the face off.
- And here we go, the Russians win position
and immediately start up their attack.
- Federal have gets
checked hard into the boards.
- But he's going to shout has the puck
now and he passes it to center, he shoots?
- Wow, what a save by the goalie!
- All right, the puck is back in play now.
- And the board is on a breakaway.
- He is flying down the ice.
- The defenders can't keep up.
- Slap shot, he scores.
- What an amazing goal!
(crowd cheering)
(upbeat music)
- All right, so hockey is
the Canadian national sport.
- Well, actually it isn't.
- It isn't. - Yeah, it isn't.
- What is it?
- La Crosse.
- La Crosse. - La Crosse.
- But anyway, we don't have a
lesson about real cross today.
- Not yet.
- No, but actually all
Canadians love hockey.
Like, we start playing hockey
when we're about two years old.
- Yeah, I've heard that
some Canadian children
learn how to skate before
they learn how to walk.
- It's totally common.
- Well, it is a great
sport, very, very exciting.
It's very fast paced,
and it's very aggressive.
That's what I like about it.
- I know.
- Not violent, but very aggressive.
- Yeah, but you know what?
I must tell you that I
am not a good Canadian.
- You're not a hockey fan?
- No, I'm really.
- Yeah, I really hate hockey.
- Why?
- You know what, the puck is so small.
It's hard to see where
it is on the ice and it's
cold and these guys
are fighting, and anyway.
- Have you ever been to a hockey game?
- Yeah, many times.
And I just find that
the puck is really small.
- Maybe you just need better seats, maybe.
- Well, what do you
guys think about hockey?
We'll post some videos
and some pictures of hockey
on the comments section
so you can more or less see
a little bit more about
this really interesting
sport and tell us what
you think about it.
- Yeah, so visit our
website, EnglishPod.
com and you'll find some
interesting stuff about hockey, right?
- Exactly.
- And also lots of other great lessons.
- I exactly.
And also, if you have any
questions or doubts about
the less, you can leave
your questions on the site.
- Mm-hmm.
- All right, we're out of time.
We'll see you guys next time.
- Thanks for listening, and goodbye.
(upbeat music)